The first-class mage exam will now begin.
これより一級魔法使い選抜試験を行う。
パーティー戦だ　総勢５７名。
You will be tested as parties.
The 57 exam-takers will split into teams
of three for the first test.
３人１組のパーティーに分かれ試験を受けてもらう。
Beyond Journey's End
Episode 19: Well-Laid Plans
ほら…　やりゃできんだよ…。
See? I knew you could do it.
えへへ…　そうかなぁ…。
You think so?
ラヴィーネは乱暴だけれども
Lawine is rough, but she
pulls me along with her.
ちゃんと私を引っ張ってくれるんだ
Our first battle against a dragon is tomorrow.
いよいよ明日は竜との初戦闘だな
怖いのか？　アイゼン震えているぞ
Are you scared, Eisen?
You're shaking.
ああ
Yeah.
I see. In that case...
そうか　なら…
Wait, what? You're scared?
え？　怖いの？
Yeah.
ああ
I see. I'm scared, too.
そうか…
僕も怖い
What kind of conversation is this?
何？　この会話ハッハッハ
他の冒険者をまねて鼓舞するつもりだったんだが…
I thought I'd copy other adventurers
and inspire you, but...
I'm sorry. It doesn't seem to have worked.
すまないうまくいかなかったみたいだ
いいやおかげで緊張がほぐれた
No. Thanks to you, I'm no longer tense.
Himmel, just be yourself.
ヒンメル自然体でいいですよ
こういうのは　きっと
I'm sure this sort of thing
differs from party to party.
冒険の仲間ごとに変わってくるものです
そうだね
You're right.
なるほど確かに仲間ごとに違うみたいだ。
I see. It really does differ
from party to party.
We finally caught a Stille.
やっと捕まえられましたね　隕鉄鳥。
これで　ひと安心ですね。
Now we don't have to worry.
気楽なこと言ってくれるね。
Why are you so relaxed?
これから先の方が大変なんだよ。
The hard part's still to come.
僕らは隕鉄鳥を
We have to keep our Stille
from being stolen by other parties.
他のパーティーに奪われないように守らなければならない。
対人戦の時間だ。
It's time to fight other mages.
Let's review what we learned
from observing the Stille.
それじゃあ　隕鉄鳥を観察した結果をまとめようか。
まずはフリーレンの言った通り
First, like Frieren said, those birds
fly faster than the speed of sound.
あの鳥は音速を超えて飛行する。
この速度に追い付くことは不可能だね。
We could never catch up to it at that speed.
さらに　竜みたいに頑丈で
Furthermore, they're as tough as dragons.
Common attack spells have no effect,
and they break free of most restraints.
並の攻撃魔法じゃびくともしないし
拘束も破られる。
おまけに　魔力にとても敏感だ。
On top of that, they're sensitive to mana.
こっちが魔力を抑えて近づいてもすぐに逃げられちまう。
Even when we suppress our mana to
approach one, it quickly flies away.
何より最大の問題は
The biggest problem of all is because the
Stille themselves have practically no mana,
隕鉄鳥が魔力をほとんど持っていないせいで
we can't find them using mana detection.
魔力探知ができないってことだな。
おかげで　今どこにいるのかさっぱり分からねえ。
Because of that, we have
no idea where they are now.
総数も不明だ。
We don't know how many there are either.
見つけられたのも結局昨日の午前中の３回だけだしね。
The only ones we ever spotted were
those three yesterday morning.
受験者が探し回っているから警戒しちゃってるんだと思う。
They're probably being cautious because
the test-takers are searching for them.
Worst case, they might
never show themselves again.
最悪　もう姿を現さないかも。
And even if we do find one,
we have no idea how to catch it.
そもそも見つけられたとしても
どう捕らえるのか見当もつかねえ。
それなら大丈夫だよ。
Don't worry about that.
実は昨日の夜
Last night I experimented with a spell
that might be useful for catching a Stille.
隕鉄鳥を捕らえるのに役に立つかもしれない
魔法の実験をしていたんだよね。
I remember you going out.
確かに出かけてたねどんな魔法なの？
What kind of spell is it?
カンネには　もう見せたよ。
I already showed you, Kanne.
A spell that captures a bird.
「鳥を捕まえる魔法」。
It's a folk spell developed by
a tribe of hunters during an era
今よりも　ずっと魔法使いが多くて魔法が一般的だった時代に
狩猟を生業とする一族が編み出した民間魔法だよ。
when mages and magic were far more common.
Come to think of it, you did use
a spell to restrain that creature.
そういえば魔法で動きを封じていたね。
But wasn't that a monster and not a bird?
でも　あれは鳥じゃなくて魔物じゃ…。
It's folk magic, after all.
民間魔法だからね。
大ざっぱに鳥みたいなやつは全部　捕らえられるみたい。
It appears it can be used to capture
anything that broadly resembles a bird.
It's a powerful binding spell.
強力な拘束魔法だし隕鉄鳥にも通用すると思う。
I think it'll probably work on the Stille.
Why didn't you say so earlier?
何で　それを黙っていたんだよ。
それを使えば　昨日の時点で捕まえられていたじゃねえか。
We could've caught one yesterday
if we'd used that.
Actually, we couldn't have.
そうもいかないんだよね。　ん？
この魔法の射程は５０ｃｍ。
That spell's range is 50 centimeters.
そこまでは近づかないとダメなんだ。
You have to get that close to use it.
５０ｃｍって…。
Fifty centimeters?
今まで　どのくらいまで近づけたっけ？
How close have we gotten so far?
最大で３ｍだね。
Three meters was the closest.
しかも２０ｍくらい近づいた時点で
Not only that, but they noticed us
by the time we got within 20 meters of them.
こっちの存在に気が付いているみたい。
So we're one step short
of meeting the requirements.
現状　あと一歩ってところだね。
That's one huge step.
随分でっけぇ一歩だなぁ…。
一応　確認だけど
Just to confirm, it's difficult for you two
to stop the Stille with your magic, right?
２人の魔法じゃ　隕鉄鳥の足止めは難しいんだよね？
うまく凍らせられれば可能だろうが
It'd probably work if we could freeze one,
but they're sensitive to mana, tough,
and resistant to freezing.
魔力に敏感な上に頑丈で凍りにくい。
多分　動きを封じる前に逃げられちまうだろうな。
It'd probably escape before
we could fix it in place.
私の魔法なら　大量の水があれば足止めは簡単だと思うけど…。
I bet we could easily stop one with my magic
if we had access to a ton of water.
But my magic only allows me to control water.
でも　私が使えるのは水を操る魔法で
水自体を生成することはできないんだよね。
I can't create it out of nothing.
だから　水のある場所じゃないと使えないし
So I can't use it unless
there's water present,
まとまった水は魔力が通りにくいから
and mana struggles to penetrate
large bodies of water.
事前に魔力を込めておかないと難しいかな。
I'd probably have to infuse it
with my mana beforehand.
雨みたいに分散していれば
I can quickly take control of even large
amounts of water if it's scattered, like rain.
大量の水でもすぐに操れるんだけど。
でも　水に魔力を込めたら
But if I infused water with mana, the mana-
sensitive Stille would definitely stay away.
魔力に敏感な隕鉄鳥は絶対に寄ってこないだろうね。
寄ってこない…。
Stay away?
そうか　寄ってこないのか。　ん？
I see. They'd stay away.
This plan might work.
この作戦ならいけるかも。
確かに悪くはねえがリスクが高ぇな。
It's not bad, but it's risky.
他のパーティー全員にケンカを売ることになるぜ。
We'd be picking a fight
with all the other teams.
But I doubt we'll catch one otherwise.
でも多分　こうでもしないと捕まえられない。
Are you scared, Lawine?
怖いの？　ラヴィーネ。
Ow, ow, ow! You're gonna rip them off!
痛い　痛い　痛い　痛い　痛い‼取れちゃう‼　う〜！
分かったよやってやろうじゃねえか。
Fine.
Let's do this.
4th Party
Land, Second-Class Mage
取りあえず　試験終了まで潜伏してやり過ごそう。
For now, let's hide until the test is over.
4th Party
Übel, Third-Class Mage
What? That's no fun.
え〜　つまんないよ魔法使いなら堂々と戦わないと。
We're mages. We should fight openly.
4th Party
Fern, Third-Class Mage
Mages also avoid unnecessary fighting.
不要な戦いを避けるのも魔法使いだ。
あ…。
But first, we should get water.
その前に水の補充だな。
確か　中央に湖があったはずだ。
I think there was a lake
in the middle of the area.
しかし　隕鉄鳥が早い段階で確保できて　よかったよ。
Either way, I'm glad
we caught a Stille so quickly.
あとは日没まで潜伏すれば第一次試験は通過できる。
If we can remain hidden until sunset,
we'll pass the first test.
フフっ。
どうした？
What is it?
Looks like it won't be that easy.
どうやら　そう　うまくはいかないみたいだ。
これってさ道だと思っていたけれども
I thought this was a road,
but it's actually a dry riverbed.
枯れた川だよね。
しかも似たような地形が何か所もあった。
Not only that, but I saw similar
terrain in a few other places.
確か　試験区域を囲むように結界が張られているんですよね。
Isn't there a barrier around the testing area?
ああ　試験では定番だね。
Yeah. That's standard for tests.
塵すら通さない強力な対物理結界だよ。
They're powerful physical barriers
that keep out even specks of dust.
もしかして水も通さないんですか？
Do they block water, too?
あ…。
Oh.
枯れ具合から見て結界を張ったのは
Judging by the dryness,
the barrier was erected over a week ago.
１週間以上前だね。
では　水のほとんどは
Then most of the water will have collected
in the lake in the middle of the valley.
盆地の真ん中にある湖に集まっていますね。
私たち受験者も生き物ですから
Since the test-takers are living creatures,
活動するのにはある程度　水が必要です。
we need some amount of water to stay active.
だからって湖の周りに受験者が
That doesn't guarantee test-takers
would gather around the lake.
まとまっているとは限らないでしょ。
You're right.
そうですね。
We can carry water with us.
私たちは水を持ち歩けます。
でも　同じ生き物である隕鉄鳥は　そうは　いかない。
But the Stille, which are
also living creatures, cannot.
I see. And those who have realized that
なるほどそれに気が付いた連中が
最大の水場である湖の周りに張り込んでいるわけか。
will be waiting around the lake,
the largest body of water in the area.
ん？
Okay, I've made my decision.
We'll give up on finding water.
よし決めたもう水は諦めなさい。
さすがに　それはきついって既に喉からからなんだけど。
That'll be tough. I'm already parched.
小さな池くらいなら探せばあるだろ。
I'm sure we can find a small pond.
Is that sanitary?
それ衛生的にどうなのよ？煮沸すれば何とか…。
Perhaps if we boil it.
んっ！
フフ…。
ヘッ。
8th Party
Scharf, Third-Class Mage
Ehre, Second-Class Mage
面倒くせぇな殺すつもりで撃ったんだぜ。
8th Party
Wirbel, Second-Class Mage
What a pain in the ass.
I was shooting to kill.
今のに反応できんのかよ。
You're quick enough to react to that?
まぁ　いいや　隕鉄鳥の入ったカゴを置いていけ。
Well, whatever.
Leave the cage with the Stille.
嫌だって言ったら？
And if we refuse?
なら　言葉は不要だな。
Then there's no need for words.
湖の方向
The lake is that way.
ん…？
湖を凍らせやがった。
They froze the lake.
おいおい　何のつもりだ。　シャレにならんぞ。
Seriously? What are they doing?
This isn't funny.
That's the mana of one of
the 2nd party's members.
この魔力第２パーティーのヤツだな。
何　考えてやがる。
What are they thinking?
他のパーティー全員を敵に回すつもりか…。
Are they trying to antagonize
all the other parties?
うぅ…！
何をやっておる‼　早く溶かせ‼
What are you doing?
Hurry up and melt it!
デンケン　どうする？
Denken, what should we do?
時間と労力の無駄だ。
It's a waste of time and effort.
13th Party
Denken, Second-Class Mage
There's no point in melting it now.
溶かしたところで意味はない。
13th Party
Richter, Second-Class Mage
これほど派手に魔法を使われたら
After that showy display of magic,
the Stille won't come near this lake again.
13th Party
Laufen, Third-Class Mage
隕鉄鳥はもう　この湖には近づかない。
隕鉄鳥は第２パーティーから奪うぞ。
We'll steal our Stille from the 2nd party.
If they went this wild,
they must have a plan to catch one.
これだけ暴れたということは
隕鉄鳥を捕獲する算段があるということだ。
フリーレン様一体　何をするつもりですか…
Ms. Frieren, what are you doing?
このまま一度　ばらけよう。
Let's scatter for now.
We have to melt the frozen lake quickly!
凍った湖を早く溶かすんだ！
Those fools.
愚かだな。
Using that much magic to melt the ice
will make the lake truly useless.
こんなに盛大に魔法を使って氷を溶かせば
この湖は本格的に使い物にならなくなる。
The Stille won't come near here again.
隕鉄鳥はもう　ここには寄りつかん。
Let's go.
Yeah.
That way!
Those who realized that are searching
for other watering holes,
それに気が付いた連中が他の水場を探しているようだが…。
魔力探知が甘過ぎるあれでは空の脅威に対処できん。
but their mana detection is inadequate.
They won't be able to handle airborne threats.
未熟だな。
They're inexperienced.
Apparently the 2nd party froze the lake.
第２パーティーが湖を凍らせたらしいぞ。
試験をむちゃくちゃにするつもりか？
Are they trying to ruin the test?
Ruin it? No.
むちゃくちゃだと？　違うな。
これは第２パーティーが練った入念な計画だ。
The 2nd party has a well-laid plan.
Until we unravel it, we won't get anywhere.
それを　ひもとかん限りどうにもならん。
魔物にやられたか。
Monsters got them.
もう死んでいる。
They're already dead.
行くぞ。
Let's go.
Sir, let's at least take them down.
爺さんせめて降ろしてあげようよ。
見えていないわけではないだろう。
You can see them, can't you?
上空を旋回している。
They're circling above.
１匹や２匹ではない。
Not just one or two of them either.
There's magic on those corpses.
降ろそうとすればヤツらに探知されるぞ。
They'll detect you
if you try to take them down.
Geisel. That's how they lure
and hunt their next prey.
屍誘鳥　こいつらは　そうやって次の獲物を誘って狩りをする。
このパーティーはまんまと術中に　はまり
This party fell for their trap
and got themselves killed.
全滅したわけだ。
異常だね。
It's strange that they chose
こんな魔物がいる場所を試験区域に選ぶだなんて
to administer the test in an area
inhabited by monsters like these.
受験者が死ぬのを何とも思っていないみたいだ。
It's like they think nothing
of the test-takers dying.
ラオフェンは一級の試験を受けるのが初めてだったな。
Laufen, this is your first time
taking the first-class exam, isn't it?
理由は極めて単純だ。ん？
Their reasoning is incredibly simple.
この程度で死ぬヤツは
Anyone who would die here is
unqualified to be a first-class mage.
一級魔法使いにはいらないということだ。
大陸魔法協会は
The Continental Magic Association
一級魔法使いの質を気にしているからな。
is very mindful of maintaining
the quality of first-class mages.
魔王軍と戦っていた時代の強く誇り高い魔法使いを
There are those who still dream
of the powerful and noble mages
who fought the Demon King's forces.
いまだに夢見ている連中がいるのさ。
Damn their outdated ideas.
時代遅れも甚だしい。
意外だな　デンケン。
I'm surprised, Denken.
I thought you'd be on their side.
あんたは　それを支持する側の人間だと思っていた。
魔法使いに質など　いらん。
The quality of a mage is irrelevant.
一級魔法使いは　ただ単に権威の象徴であればいいのだ。
First-class mages need only
be symbols of power.
魔法使いとしての力量がいくらあっても
No matter how powerful you are,
unless you can control people's hearts,
you're as good as powerless.
人心を掌握できなければ無力も同じ。
儂は自分よりはるかに優れた魔法使いが
I've seen countless mages
far more skilled than myself
失脚し　迫害される様を山ほど見てきた。
fall from power and be persecuted.
大きな力は恐れられる恐れの権威など長続きせん。
Great power is feared,
and rule by fear doesn't last long.
Besides, magic isn't a noble thing.
それに　魔法は誇り高いものでも何でもない。
なるほど　あんたくらい弱いのがちょうどいいってわけだ。
I see. So someone as weak as you
is perfect for the job.
言ってくれるな　若造が。
Watch your tongue, boy.
お前くらいなら目を瞑っていても勝てるわ。
I could beat you with my eyes closed.
ん…。
We've had no luck detecting the 2nd party.
全然　探知できないね第２パーティー。
魔力を隠して潜伏しているな。
They're concealing their mana and hiding.
This place, too. All the watering holes
we've seen are the same.
ここもだな今まで見てきた水場　全部だ。
ん？
It's faint, but there's mana in the water.
わずかだが水に魔力が込められている。
I don't sense anything.
何も感じない…。
ん〜　分かる？
Do you?
No. Is it the 2nd party?
俺も分からん第２パーティーの仕業か？
きっと　かけた本人すら感知できないだろう。
I doubt even the person
who cast it could detect it.
それほどに微量だ。
There's that little in it.
だが　隕鉄鳥なら感知できる。
But a Stille could sense it.
この水場にはもう近づかないだろう。
They won't come near this water again.
What's the point of doing this?
こんなことして何が…。
I see. There's a watering hole somewhere
that doesn't contain mana.
そっか　どこかに魔力を込めていない水場がある。
その近くに第２パーティーは必ずいる。
And that's where the 2nd party will be.
どう捜すの？
How will we find it?
I'm going to rest a bit.
少し休む。
Denken.
デンケン。　試験区域は広大だ。
The testing area is enormous.
本気で潜伏する魔法使いを見つけられるわけなかろう。
It'd be impossible to find a mage
who truly doesn't want to be found.
We'll wait.
They'll show us where they are eventually.
池や泉に手当たり次第に魔力を込めてきたよ。
I infused every lake and pond
I could find with mana.
把握できていない水場がある可能性は　まだあるけど…。
It's possible there are bodies of water
we don't know about, though.
隕鉄鳥の使える水場が制限されるだけでも十分だよ。
Just limiting the watering holes
the Stille can use is enough.
じゃあ　私はここで隕鉄鳥を待ち伏せするよ。
I'll wait here for a Stille.
マジかよ…　魔力って完全に消せるもんなんだな。
Seriously? It's possible to completely
suppress your mana?
完全じゃないよ。
Not completely.
さすがに動けば少しは魔力が漏れる。
When I move, I release a little mana. See?
ほら。
分かんねえよ。
I can't sense it.
私たちは見張りだな。
We'll stand watch.
足　引っ張んなよ。　うっさい。
Don't hold us back.
Shut up.
雨さえ降れば戦力になれるんだけどね。
If it'd just rain,
I could be useful in a fight.
全部　結界に弾かれちまうもんな。
But the barrier would deflect all of it.
ん！
Frieren, did you do it?
フリーレン　やったか？
他のパーティーにケンカを売ったかいがあったぜ。
It was worth picking a fight
with the other parties.
これで　第一次試験突破だね。
Now we'll pass the first test.
いや。
No.
見つけた。
Found them.
So they used magic after all.
やはり魔法を使いおったな。
どんなに優秀な魔法使いでもこの瞬間だけはごまかせん。
Not even the most skilled mage
can conceal that moment.
誰かに探知された早く　ここから…。
Someone's detected us.
We should get away from here.
逃げるのは　もう遅いみたいだね。
Looks like it's too late to run.
Jubelade.
花弁を鋼鉄に変える魔法。
石を弾丸に変える魔法。
Doragate.
まるで砲弾…
It's like a cannon.
また　距離を取った
She backed off again.
Her technique is refined
and shows no openings, but it's old.
洗練されていて隙がないけれども
古い戦い方だ
私のお爺ちゃんと戦っているみたい…
It's like fighting against my grandfather.
Ordinary offensive magic and defensive magic.
一般攻撃魔法と防御魔法。
基礎的な魔法しか使わないのね。
You only use basic spells.
手の内は見せないつもりかしら？
Are you playing things close to the chest?
戦闘では基礎的な魔法以外は使わないように言われてますから。
I was taught to only use
basic spells in combat.
That's your master's philosophy, then?
あなたの師匠の方針なのね。
Yes. She said it's enough
to defeat mages of this era.
はい　この時代の魔法使いならそれだけで十分だと。
そう。
Oh, yeah?
まただ
Again. What is this feeling of wrongness?
何だろうね　この違和感は
まるで　熟練の魔法使いと対峙しているみたいだ
It's like I'm fighting an experienced mage.
あなたも難儀ね　そんな戦い方
You're going to struggle.
If you fought Wirbel with your technique,
you'd be dead by now.
ヴィアベルが相手だったら今頃は死んでいたわよ。
That doesn't make sense.
それは　おかしいです。
You're the strongest one here, aren't you?
この中で　一番強いのはあなたですよね。
フフ…。
Wirbel is the captain of the
Northern Magic Corps that fought
ヴィアベルは魔王軍の残党と戦ってきた　北部魔法隊の隊長よ。
against the remnants
of the Demon King's forces.
実戦経験の桁が違う。
He has far more experience in battle.
あいつが使うのは品性のまるでない
His magic is devoid of character.
勝つための卑怯な魔法。
It's underhanded,
for the sole purpose of winning.
今　ヴィアベルと戦ってる子
The girl fighting Wirbel now
will probably be killed.
多分　殺されちゃうわよ。
そうですか。
Is that so?
What hells have you seen?
I'll take your head off.
I'll crush her.
He's strong.
Interesting. Try me.
This is impressive.
What's this sound?
You old fart.
I've always killed everyone I had to.
Episode 20
Necessary Killing